so let's give a big warm welcome to
Geshe Michael
[Applause]
thank you that's nice to see so many
friends and thank you for coming yeah so
I was teaching in China a few years ago
and some of my Chinese friends asked me
if I could teach
the diamond cutter Sutra there's a
commentary that was written about 1300
years ago by a master Kamala Sheila and
Kamala Sheila's famous in Tibet all
systems of meditation and Tibet came
from him he wrote three great books
about meditation called Bhavana karma
and so and he actually came to Tibet
briefly and then he wrote this
incredible commentary to the diamond
cutter Sutra and it was translated into
Tibetan and then it was lost in in
Sanskrit and also in Chinese so it
exists only in Tibetan now and we don't
have the original to compare and the
translation is very corrupted so it's a
lot of fun for me to try to figure out
what it said and I've been working on it
for about five years and now I feel
comfortable with it and I feel really
happy about it and now we're translating
it in our translation program so we have
a goal of translating a hundred and
eight books from ancient India and and
then writing commentaries on them we
finished the 65 of them we have 31
translations in progress and I brought
some of the translations
you got those oh I'm gonna set up set
them out during the break so you guys
can check them out but we have a new
college in Sedona we just finished our
first year this is a thousand pages of
translations of ancient books by our
team and they're doing about 2,000 pages
a year now and so Carmel our Sheila is
one of them and so I've been teaching it
in a retreat setting at our diamond
mountain retreat center and people have
been coming to do deep retreat there
from about 20 countries and
so when I come to New York I'd like to
just give you a taste of it so tonight
we've reached sort of the end of the
Sutra and at the very end of the Sutra
there's a very beautiful poem the Buddha
breaks into a special poem and that poem
became very very famous in Tibet in
India and it became so famous that it's
treated as a mantra no we call an open
mantra so people recited for example the
monks and nuns twice a month have to
recite it before the during the sojeong
ceremony for confession they have to
recite it and then they snap their
fingers and they're supposed to remember
impermanence and it happens in many many
texts so I thought I would go straight
there and and work on that with you this
final verse and give you come unless
Sheila's take on it and then then I
thought next time I come we'll just do a
review of the whole sutra which is very
beautiful the sutra was spoken by Lord
Buddha two and a half thousand years ago
in a place called travesty which I've
been to they found they found it it was
buried about thirty feet underground and
they followed the travelogue of chuan
Sung who was a great Tong dynasty monk
from China he walked to India it took
him 17 years well he walks through India
he studied with all the great masters
during the seven hundreds and he counted
his steps and because of his record
which is called the great Tong dynasty
record of the western regions we were
able to find travesty and it's a
beautiful place Buddha was teaching in a
garden called jetavana which means the
gardens of prince Jetta and and this
garden was part of a larger Park that
was bought for the Buddha by somebody
named another pin Dada
uh-uh means not write in Sanskrit nada
means protector pinda means food and pen
Dada means the person who gives food to
the poor so he was a very wealthy
businessman so I think it's kind of cool
carmella Sheela likes to say that the
Buddha you know was teaching in a garden
near a great city and the place was
bought by a politician and a businessman
and and then Buddha slowly in the city
he tamed them and he teaches them and
it's to me it's sort of beautiful that
he's come lishchyna makes a point that
Buddha is both engaging in the world and
not engaging in the world he's in the
garden he's teaching this beautiful
teaching in the garden but he's teaching
it because of a businessman and a
politician and it's kind of beautiful
how the Buddha manages to to reach
everybody in the room with this teaching
and that's what we've tried to do with
the diamond cutter Institute we we used
the diamond cutter Sutra as the basis of
it and it's by the way the oldest
printed book in the world with a date it
was dated 800 the Chinese copy is the it
was found in the Denholm desert case and
we'd like to try to teach it to normal
people and so we tried we started I
don't know how long ago eight years
eight years ago we just started trying
to teach the principles of the diamond
cutter you know Sutra to normal people
without making it religious we tried to
make it something that everyone could
listen to tomorrow day after tomorrow we
leave for India would teach it at
Banaras Hindu University where they're
very hard core Hindus then we'll teach
it to the Gujarat Chamber of Commerce
and then we'll go to Almaty Kazakhstan I
think last year was 800 800 Muslims came
and learned the diamond cutter sutra
then we go to Vienna and we've been able
to teach it all over the world we for
example we taught it to the mayor's
office of Buenos Aires
and we taught it to all the mayor and
his staff and people are using it for
running large organizations the diamond
cutter Sutra and he took me into his
office personally after the presentation
and he asked me can I use this
principles of karma to become president
of the country and he pointed out that
they call it the pink house which is
their white house you can see it from
the window of his office so you know I
explained to him well you're gonna have
to do these four steps you're gonna have
to collect the Karma and the four steps
involve helping someone else who would
like to be president and he's very
strange guy he is very intelligent you
know which is unusual and a politician
and he looked at me and he said okay
I'll give it a shot you know and he was
elected president last December Mauricio
Macri and he's running the country on
the diamond cutter and it's it's kind of
cool and the economy is picking it's one
of the best growing economies in the
world right now it was a mess before
that so he's kind of using these
principles I don't know Scott you have
this thing Scott also taught it in the
Congress in Mexico and I read his wife
taught at MIT Business School and people
enjoy it you know people really like it
so I thought tonight I'll show you how
we teach it to business people or
politicians and then and then we'll go
deeper into the Sanskrit and we'll go
deep into the text but I thought it
might be fun for you to see how we teach
the diamond cutter Sutra to say a large
Muslim audience or you know the south
and we might be in Dubai or we're going
to Vienna after that so I'll I'll just
show you now when I pull this out you
shouldn't fall asleep
where is France
my assistant Oh
okay you ready he's my okay I like to
teach you know emptiness is the big
subject of the diamond cutter Sutra and
diamonds have a big lot to do with
emptiness and the title of the Sutra is
no mistake and I like to teach emptiness
with a pen I I got some complaints I was
in Singapore and and one of the people
said I'd I want my money back and I said
why and they said well you teach the pen
every time you come and at least give us
back that much money you know like 15
minutes of money then my my own friends
I don't know you guys know long rim and
Shalom sir can can you tell I'm super
know what's his path of preparation
turret mo super Jojo third third level
of a certain spiritual path if you get a
good explanation of the pen if you
understand emptiness intellectually and
it doesn't matter you're Muslim or your
Communist Party of China or you're a
Catholic in them in New Mexico Congress
if you understand it according to
Buddhism you cannot be born in a lower
realm
you cannot go down after you die you you
must become a human or better so I don't
tell audiences all over the world I
don't tell the President of Argentina
I'm trying to protect you from the lower
realms but it's true okay and that's
what I keep repeating it okay so don't
think I'm weird
I do remember teaching it last year okay
so let's go okay
and it'll be painless if you answer me
quickly so I'm supposed to ask questions
and then and then you answer this is an
ancient Buddhist way of teaching okay
what is this thing
okay Francis I expect you to help me
okay second question if a small dog
comes in here and he comes down to here
and he comes up here in the small puppy
dog right Francis and I say and I show
this pen to him well will he do yeah he
will buy it yeah so does the dog still
there's a pen no he sees it as something
to cheer right okay Francis now I got a
serious question for you who's right the
human or the dog both yeah you're right
okay now now we reach emptiness okay
and it sounds ridiculously simple and
and it is and all the Buddhist teachers
would be out of business if people
learned it cuz that's all there is to
say about it but if okay Francis you
ready if I put this thing here and all
the humans go out of the room and all
the dogs go out of the room and this
room is empty completely empty at that
time is this a pin or a chew toy which
one nothing you're so smart we practiced
backstitch yeah at that time it's
nothing and that's emptiness okay that's
the mean there's nothing more than that
and then that about emptiness and you
can use emptiness to become the
president of Argentina or you can use it
to run our large company we just gave
programs to the largest insurance
company in the world in Shenzhen China
to the HR department which has a million
and a half employees and and they're
using it now the two husbands
presentation it's called two husbands in
the kitchen okay
so I'm going to teach it to you guys and
then we'll get to the diamond cutter
Sutra okay but actually these two skills
is everything you need to know you know
the diamond cutter if you know these two
things okay
so all the men in the world had a
meeting recently we decided equal rights
for women before it was divided into
women should cook and and and take care
of the children and men should make the
money but then we decided that women
could also make the money and then we
could watch football on TV and so this
kind of became popular around the world
and let's say I'm a I'm a housewife in
China or something okay and now I'm
liberated I can work all day and take
care of the kids and do the cooking okay
you know and then I have two kids we'd
be my two kids you two guys
Lin Chen oh ma okay so these are my two
kids then okay I just got to tell you
guys something mommy
mommy's boss said she has to come in
early tomorrow because I have to be on
an international phone call so we're an
international company mommy's company
and I just want to ask you guys to be
ready tomorrow morning like one hour
early okay and have your shoes on have
your homework done okay you guys agree
come on just agree okay then then okay
next morning you walk in the kids room
you open the door and they're jumping on
the bed you gotta jump on the bed yeah
okay that'll do I'm like you guys didn't
get ready mommy's gotta go early did you
forget you're too shy then okay then I'm
mommy says I can't believe you are the
stupidest kids in New York City you know
I just can't believe it I was so clear
that you had to be ready okay then who
heard mommy call them the stupidest kids
in New York yeah
mommy and the kids okay but it's the
same principle with Francis you see if I
see my hand open I plan to karma the
awareness of what I'm doing plants of
karma you see and when I'm aware that
I'm yelling at my two kids when I hear
my words in my own ear it that's what
plants are karma okay so now I've got a
seed in my mind karmic seed in my mind a
couple of thousand actually okay now I
don't know next week I'm like working
really hard and I had to stay late and
I'm tired I brought the kids home I went
and picked up groceries you know and I'm
really exhausted wait I need my husband
here are you ready you can be here in
front of the piano and trust you so I'm
tired by the way this is better than the
diamond cutter Sutra don't worry
then I'm coming home I'm exhausted
you know I just want a hug okay that's
all that men do anymore they don't work
they never took care of the kids and
they didn't cook so I'm just exhausted
I'm just looking forward to having a hug
really you know you've probably been
there if you're married you just
exhausted and you just want to come home
and you want somebody to hug you right
so you come home and you open the door
and you go and they say okay then you're
like I didn't do anything you know and
it's almost like a single word I didn't
do anything I didn't do anything he
started yelling at me I didn't do
anything
you know I didn't even say anything I
just walked in the door and he still
calls me stupid you know I'll tell you
what you're stupid okay by the way why
are there two husbands in my kitchen now
this you gotta understand okay
this husband comes from I'm sorry this
husband comes from nothing I didn't do
anything
okay ready take a deep breath I didn't
do anything it's like one word okay I
didn't do anything and he started
screaming at me okay got it
now this husband he's a result of a seed
that I planted last week with my two
kids okay why I called them stupid
what I call them stupidest kids in New
York right now I remember then that
planted a seed in my mind when I opened
the door the seed open and then from my
mind okay like the pen that's why we did
the pen first from my mind comes an
image of a screaming husband okay so
this one came from me okay this one
comes from a seed in my mind can I say I
didn't do anything
why not I yelled at the kids okay that's
where he's coming from
all right this husband it's coming from
me because I did the same thing last
week okay got it so you can't say I need
anything you did do something you did
something last week okay now we can go
deeper now we go to diamond cutter Sutra
okay this husband doesn't come from me
this husband does come from me okay one
of them exists and one of them doesn't
exist which is which is he exists or not
no it doesn't exist okay
Buddha said more in the diamond cutter
he said doesn't exist couldn't exist and
never will exist okay this husband is
impossible okay got it
how about this husband yeah he exists
okay he comes from me okay now where's
the emptiness here emptiness means
something you thought was there was not
there where's the emptiness he's him
he's not there and he never was there
okay what which husband I didn't do
anything husband okay got it
just nod okay this husband cannot exist
this husband comes from nowhere okay I
didn't know anything this husband comes
from what I said to my kids last week
okay
this husband exists okay garleon this
one is emptiness that's the meaning of
emptiness he can't exist he never
existed there is nothing in your world
which is not coming directly from how
you treat other people there is nothing
in your world that does not come
directly from how you treat other people
okay so this one who's I didn't do
anything he doesn't exist
okay now you want to go deeper
in China they got mom but I'm getting
used to in New York okay
yeah do I get upset when I come in I'm
tired when I come in my kitchen and my
husband starts screaming at me do I get
upset yeah if he calls me stupid
I'm not stupid you're stupid okay
that's normal right okay now hmm then I
get angry right I get angry I didn't do
anything
he called me stupid now answer me
Frances this is harder which husband am
i angry at I'm gonna call him number one
and him number two which husband of my
angry I when I said no I'm not stupid
you're stupid yeah number one why I
think he's not my fault I think he's not
my fault
got it if I understand he's my fault
can I get angry no he's your fault
I need anything yes you did you yelled
at your kids I say I can't do something
okay then you're not gonna get upset at
this one you can't get upset at this one
okay if you understand karma you cannot
get upset on this one and in fact the
only way to reach nirvana according to
the Buddha is that is to understand
where things are coming from that's the
only way to stop anger permanently is to
understand where things you get angry
are coming from got in you can't get
angry okay let's say I understand it is
coming from me okay do it again
no you
it's okay you all right then if you
wanna yell you can go in the bathroom
you know look in the mirror yeah so
stupid
understand that's emptiness that's how
you used emptiness in your real life
okay he's not here and he was never here
and where he's standing is empty there's
no such there's no husband there there's
not really two husbands in the kitchen
there's only one right which one
number two the one who came from me if
you understand that is it and you're
really thinking about it when you open
the door
is it possible to collect another karma
is it possible to say you're stupid I
mean you can but you will prove that you
are stupid garnish okay you husband's
can sit down yeah all right now we'll go
now you're ready for the diamond cutter
okay you weren't ready before I'm not
sure ready now but anyway
okay last verse of the diamond cutter
very very very very famous okay if the
Bible is famous in the West the diamond
cutter is the most famous book in the in
the east
okay and the last verse is and I gave
you this reading okay it's called the
nine messages from the diamond cutter
sitter there are nine messages in this
verse okay it took me five days to teach
it recently at our retreat center I'm
gonna do it in two nights I don't know I
better get my clock out
is there a clock okay all right and they
did make refreshments for you guys right
good
are they good refreshments or cheap
refreshments very good okay all right
see anything brought about by causes as
like a star and obstruction of the eye a
lamp an illusion the do or a bubble a
dream or lightning
or else a cloud thorocotomy rom depo my
Avishai aboot bottom Shabnam Java da
Brahm cha even blush Tavia Sanskrit umm
very famous okay this is the last words
of the of the most famous book in Asia
okay
and it's the book we named our company
after go to the second page you got
Francis's dog with the pen in his mouth
okay yeah I know you got cats but we're
just pretending okay and he's got a pen
in his mouth to remind you that the pen
is coming from you okay the the dog
doesn't see a pen
the dog has different seats the fact
that a dog wants to chew it and you want
to write with it is proof of emptiness
okay it proves that that thing is coming
from the mind of the observer cool just
that simple thing proves that the world
is coming from you okay don't forget
then we got the two husbands
number one is on the left that's Tim he
does not exist
he's emptiness okay he's emptiness he's
not there why he's I didn't do anything
okay there's nothing in the world which
is I didn't do anything because you
always did something okay according to
Buddhism you always did something
everything is coming from you okay
got it the second husband is yelling
he's real okay
but you don't feel so angry because you
realize he's coming from what you did
last week if you don't like the way your
husband talks just talk to your kids
nicer next week okay what's sansara
what's sansara Wheel of Life right there
there's big sense all right you go to
hell realms you you get reborn as a fish
okay that's a big son sir there are
little sensors going on every five
minutes in your life okay there's a
little one just here okay you yell at
your kids that plants a seed in your
mind right you come home your husband
calls you stupid then you
call him stupid you planned another city
in your mind then next week the kids act
up and it's called a vicious cycle we
call Sun solar right in Buddhism we call
so sorry
you are triggering vicious cycles every
few minutes your life is a long story of
vicious cycles okay you're responding to
people you don't like by being bad to
them then you meet more bad people that
you don't like and then you keep putting
these cycles into motion okay
karmic cycles all right so Buddha says
there are nine messages I can give you
to help you okay and the first is star
called Parrikar say tariqa tariqa
sanskrit root term means to cross over
like Tara is the angel who can help you
cross over suffering okay so and
transportation comes from that turn okay
so tariqa in in ancient india the stars
were considered to be on a on a course a
like a racetrack and they would go
around the sky like this so they're
called Terrica great coursers okay and
and there are six ways to interpret the
star okay
Buddha says your life is like a star at
the end of the diamond color Sutra he
says your life is like a star like the
Stars okay and then there are six
different ways to understand it okay and
I'm giving you the great thinkers of
Buddhism okay Vasa Pandu who lived
1700 years ago okay and wrote the he
wrote the abhidharma kosher one of the
five great books of Buddhism okay and
then I'm gonna give you commonly Sheila
okay and then I'll throw in Tony Lama da
rocha do who's one of tibet's greatest
thinkers okay and I wanted to throw in
Jamyang Sheba who's you know him
jaebum c'mon 1700s founded LeBron
Toshiki Oh famous monastery in Eastman
and then I thought to give you $10 abba
who's a famous buddhist scholar
and people like that and quench your
temper doing me I'm gonna give you six
different versions of the star okay
because each one is helpful okay and
they all wrote books about this verse
okay
and I just thought you would like to
hear from different great thinkers okay
the first one said the darkness around
the star is the misunderstanding you
have about your husband when you come in
the kitchen okay the darkness around the
star is the fact that you don't
understand your husband okay and then it
looks like he's coming from his own son
because you don't understand where your
husband comes from okay so the darkness
the reason the Buddha spoke of a star is
that the star needs darkness the star
lives in darkness and and when you came
home into the kitchen your mind was in
darkness
okay you didn't know about the seeds you
see you walked in to the kitchen and you
opened the door and you and your husband
yelled are you okay then your mind is in
dark is in the darkness you don't
understand that you planted a seed last
week that we call ignorant in Buddhism
avidya you you have a darkness in your
mind okay and because of that darkness
it seems like the husband's coming from
his own
and that's the star for the first rider
Vasa bundu okay that's his version got
it
the star is a light the star is your
husband which one yeah good who said
that
very good you should translate the tire
color well oh no you're already doing
that uh it's gonna be like the book of
ethiopia the book of Job or something
anyway I hope it doesn't take 2,000
years okay in here the star represents
in the first writers opinion was a
bundle and Camilla Sheena
they say the star represents your
husband okay and he lives in the
darkness of your mind because you don't
understand that he's coming from you
okay
now what if you get a good teaching on
the pen what if you get a good teaching
on the pan or what if you see somebody
plant a thousand dollars with a hundred
dollar bill okay what if someone gives
you a good teaching on emptiness
he says that's like the dawn okay that
understanding the pen that understanding
where your husband's are coming from
it's like the dawn and the star doesn't
stand a chance okay
the first husband has to go away but the
first husband will fail the husband
who's not your fault okay the husband
who's not coming from you will fail if
you understand where is it coming from
got it and your understanding is like
the Sun and it and when you walk in the
kitchen and your husband yells at you
and you remember that it's because you
planted a seed with your children that
remembering it's like sunlight and the
star must go away the star must recede
and then the daylight comes and you're
happy and you're not fighting with your
husband got it okay did he say something
bad to you yeah
did it hurt yeah whose fault was it
it's always don't worry all the good
stuff is your fault too okay but if you
understand that when you walk in the
kitchen then it's like a star coming up
against the Sun okay and the star has to
fit the the husband that you hate the
husband that you're angry at has to fend
cannot stay in the kitchen cannot
survive
okay got it okay we did one we got fifty
three to go second one $10 Amba a famous
scholar from de Beaune he says no no the
star is the truth of suffering okay the
stars the truth of suffering he has a
different interpretation okay the star
is the truth of suffering suffering
two--this buddha said four things that
when he got enlightened the first thing
he said was everything is pain the
second thing he said was there's a cause
for that pain third thing he said was
you could stop it and the fourth thing
he said was there's a way there's a path
okay and those are called the four
truths the four truths for a realized
being okay first teaching the buddha
ever again the first of them is called
the truth of suffering okay and it just
means the pain in your life it doesn't
mean a principle okay it doesn't refer
to a principle it means the pain in your
life okay the husband okay
the husband who hurt you okay like that
that unexpected hurt from the husband
okay
the pain that came from the husband in
the kitchen can only occur in the
darkness okay so now we have a second
kind of darkness okay you don't
understand where he's coming from you
don't understand he's coming from your
own mind and because of that darkness
where yeah in your own mind then you
feel pain okay then you feel pain if you
don't like the pain then remove the
darkness in your mind how learn how you
planning Karma all the time by how you
treat other people just
what you're doing okay and then that
darkness is gone and the star cannot
remain and it's like the Sun came again
it's like the Sun came again okay got it
if the Sun comes meaning you understand
where your husband's coming from the
pain will also go away okay that the
heart you feel okay all all hurt all
emotions of pain around any person are
coming from you you you you hurt someone
okay done it and when you understand
that the star has to go away that the
pain will actually go away all right got
it that's the second writers
interpretation of the star okay the
stars pain okay what was the first one
did you forget it already the first star
was the first husband okay
the second star is the pain you feel
when he says things to you okay that's
the second star all right
ready for a third star how many stars we
got we got six mind only school anybody
in the mine only school okay
there's a school of Buddhism called the
mind only school very popular in China
it'd be it was a hit in China for about
a thousand years okay and it says
something interesting your life revolves
through three principles your life
revolves through three principles this
is mind only school okay this is the
mind on this girl the first is things
you think are there that are not there
things you think are there which are not
there illusions
okay things you think are there but they
are not there in the kitchen which one
husband number one okay a husband I'm
not responsible for I didn't do anything
he just started yelling at me okay that
husband exists or not yeah
good now we can kick that husband out of
the kitchen and there'll be a space in
the kitchen where he used to be
understand what's the space called
emptiness that's emptiness that's
Buddhist emptiness okay
emptiness doesn't mean you close your
eyes everything's black it doesn't mean
that emptiness is a very useful powerful
thing you can you can make money you can
become president of whatever mrs. Merkle
is reading the book so there's a space
there where the first husband was and
that's called emptiness and that allows
someone else to be in the kitchen huh
the real husband who came from me okay
why husbands are like movies okay they
have to play on a white screen okay
there has to be a space for you to put
your husband that's coming from your
karma got it there's a picture coming
out of a karmic seed in your mind if you
meditate seriously by the way we're
gonna have a meditation class Sunday
right at the three jewels the new Street
jewels but we'll teach you a special
meditation if you do it regularly and
we're gonna have a 30-day challenge if
you do it regularly you will be able to
observe karmic seeds opening in your own
mind husband husband okay usually it's
too fast the movie goes so smooth that
you think it's not separate frames but
if you meditate very seriously you can
actually observe seats coming out
opening and husband to come here okay so
mind only school three things have to be
there number one a husband who was never
there
first thing okay second thing the space
that's left over when you kick him out
because he doesn't exist
got it and then there's a space there's
a white screen available for the
the real husband okay got it I'll say it
one more time mine only score which is
very high Buddhist school not the
highest but pretty cool
they say there's three things going on
everywhere not just your kitchen okay
everywhere in your life your office okay
your car you know your bathroom there's
always three things going on number one
there's somebody there that you think is
there who's not there okay cuz you think
he's not coming from you got it that's a
fake fake people all around you okay
that you think I'm not coming from you
okay got it
they don't exist got it are you
responsible for every person you ever
met in New York City you are okay I'm
sorry okay in this system okay then
if there was a person that you're not
responsible for that you ever met in
your life you can kick them out they
don't exist they never existed
okay when you remove them from the scene
it leaves a white screen and that's
called emptiness in Buddhism that's
called emptiness and because there's a
white screen you can project a real
husband onto it okay
got it which husband is that which
number yeah the real one coming from
your mind and if you meditate regularly
you can catch yourself doing it and it's
cool it's really cool because that gives
you permission to create your future
that gives you power to create your
future if everything in your world is
coming from how you treat people then
you can design 2018 I mean from June ok
something like that and I'm talking
financially you know I'm talking
health-wise I'm talking husband and wife
wise I'm talking how your meditation
goes I'm talking how your world goes
okay those things
are under your control if the kitchen
story is correct okay got it so that's
the next author he says in the absence
of okay I'm on number three page two in
the absence of the first partner the
second partner can appear okay
appearance marries emptiness okay we
need a blank screen to show the movie of
your life okay if you get this stuff you
know your life can be so amazing
millions of dollars floating around just
confu you know like strange stuff
happening okay and you can have
beautiful beautiful relationships like
in better than the movies and your
health can be weird you know you can be
65 and you feel like you're 25 and
you're doing weird stuff okay because
it's all coming from you you see if you
just know this stuff you can have what
you want in your life okay and your
meditation can be good because that's
also coming out of seat got it all right
number four this author wants to say
look the darkness is not the darkness
around the star is not just a bad thing
you can read it either way okay they're
all talking about the diamond cutter
Sutra they're all talking about the poem
at the end of the diamond cutter sitter
we'll probably won't get past the first
thing okay but this author wants to say
look the darkness around the star
doesn't just mean misunderstanding your
husband it doesn't mean that that
darkness is the white movie screen that
was left behind when you kicked out the
first husband that wasn't coming from
you that's a nice darkness darkness is a
nice thing okay that's one author that's
the white movie screen okay and it
allows the stars to shine can you
imagine a star shining without darkness
you need darkness so in that author he's
like no the darkness is this beautiful
emptiness don't pick on the darkness it
allows light to come
got it all right that was easy yeah
fifth one this is from the gardener okay
I stole this one from the gardener the
gardener lived 1,800 years ago he's the
first really great Buddhist teacher
after the Buddha okay
and he said oops sorry that's a llama
not my phone
he said look those stars are looking
down into all the bodies of water on the
planet whether it's the Pacific Ocean or
a bucket of water or a teardrop in a
child's eye
the stars are looking down and in the
wall all the bodies of water on this
world Pacific Ocean bucket of water
teardrop in a child's eye they are all
reflecting back what stars in this in
the gardener he's like he's like no no
you don't get it this star Buddha's
talking about sitar he's talking about
the stars looking down and seeing
themselves reflected back to them
related to the kitchen
I'll give we have this thing in our
school so I give a hundred bucks to
anybody who gets it right okay cancel
now I usually wait longer than that how
does it relate to the kitchen yeah who
said that okay 100 come in here after
class I'm serious that's how I make
money give it away now exactly when you
come in the kitchen and you see this
ugly face you know you're stupid you are
seeing yourself okay that the gardener
says that's what the Buddha meant with
the star forget all that darkness and
all that stuff he just means when the
star looks down the star system's down
in all the other people in all the other
people in the world the the percentage
of irritating you people the percentage
of irritating people you meet every day
is exactly the percentage of irritation
you give other people exactly
okay 63.2% it's exactly what you are you
want to know who you are tell me who you
meant today and how you felt about them
because that's exactly who you are
because you're a star watching yourself
in the water okay got it
it's depressing okay I'm sorry I like
that one that's the gardener he says
starts looking at it so you're seeing
yourself in other people and the exact
percentage according to what you do okay
all right last one this is from me I
just threw this one in because it seems
to me that one of the reasons the Buddha
mentioned a star is simply impermanent
okay
every morning the stars have to go away
okay so the Sun comes up it's brighter
and then the Sun the stars have to go
away and I put here number six on page
three hugs
hard words and partners pass okay that's
the daily fate of stars I mean the
Buddha was trying to tell people you
know all the things you love you will
lose okay everything you care for you
will lose everything you work for you
will lose okay your own body you will
lose okay and you are you're like a star
okay your condition is is no better than
a star that is that when the Sun comes
up there right then this starts a gun
okay we are like done every morning okay
we just keep dying and and and it's so
funny that I don't know how many million
people here fine I don't know
ain't 8 million people working all day
to build a house
have a family to dress a certain way to
have a certain car you will lose it all
it's crazy it's crazy what eight million
crazy people you know they should empty
out the asylums and let those people
live in their apartments and it's all
gonna go okay your your life is like a
star okay your life in this world it's
like a star we had a very sad thing
happened in our college we had a last
term was ended on Thanksgiving Day and
we played I played rock and roll with my
friends and we all danced and the
drummer died two days later eating Thai
food with his wife and he's totally he's
45 and he just dropped in and his wife's
holding him in her arms and you know and
then suddenly we all got a better lesson
than we had from the Sutra it was really
weird and she's a wreck she's she's
broken literally broken and that's the
story of your life you are a star we are
a star okay don't forget it then do
something good with your life right okay
second one um what time is it chin zone
8:30 just give me five more minutes okay
then you have refreshments in okay
second one is called the the cataract
and it's a it means a person with a
growth on their eye okay and it affects
how they see things okay a person with a
problem with their eyes
the first partner was never is not and
never will be
that's how Buddha described the first
partner okay the first partner is not
there in the kitchen and they have never
been in the kitchen and they couldn't be
in the kitchen in the future there's no
such person who I need anything that one
okay I didn't anything okay that partner
doesn't exist cannot exist will never
exist okay got it that one but we have a
defective instrument okay we have eyes
like scratches on your eyes and you see
people you see people out there who are
not there which husband number one you
see them because the instrument of
perception is defective you have a
scratch on your eye there's something
wrong with your eye okay
and all day every day since you were
born you think you see people hurting
you or making you happy who are not
coming from you but it's a scratch on
your own eye okay your instrument of
perception is defective okay your own
eyes are defective your own mind is
defective you are born defective there's
a major defect from the factory in every
human mind it's the and it's this deep
deep deep belief that someone exists out
there who's not my fault who's not
coming from me you see it I mean it's a
deepest tendency in all living creatures
Minds even ants birds fish they
according to Buddhism they have this
defect in their mind and they believe
things are are coming this way they
believe things are coming this way they
believe the pain is coming this way
don't chew on my pen that's a pen got in
the darks like draw you could be chewing
on it right it's not a fan from it
sounds like get you know relax a little
bit can you try to see it from my point
of view you know it's tasty it's got a
good consistency you know okay it me
just coming from the beholder things are
coming from the Builder but you have a
defective mind okay
that's the first one okay that's the
first one with the eye
I defer it's a scratch on your on your
eye okay second one if you understand
that the hurt the hurt disappears if you
understand it the hurt disappears it's
difficult for anyone to hurt you
okay people hurting us is probably the
greatest pain of this life right people
who hurt us
you know ex-wife's ex-husbands etc it's
probably the greatest pain in this life
okay that's the then he he says the real
hurt doesn't have to be there if you
understand about the scratch on your eye
okay they're coming from you that's a
problem with your eye okay they're not
being cruel to you or bad to you you
work bad to your kids last week duh-duh
and and you and you but you have this
ancient tendency to believe that things
are coming this way and you don't
understand they're coming this way
you are looking at scratches on your own
eye I got it your eyes are defective and
they always have been in a deep-rooted
way since you were born
since before you were born okay you were
born with a defect in your instrument of
the perception of the world you believe
every person is not coming from you
you've strongly believed that there's a
joke in Buddhism when I explained the
pen and Francis and me both agreed it
was coming this way
and you were looking at my hand and the
pen you were still thinking was coming
this way okay it's your scratch on your
eye okay
you can't happen it's it's it's born
you're born with it it's inborn okay all
right number three the partner the
kitchen the kids and the life
chandrakirti called it a hair sticking
to the porcelain sink so he says you
have a porcelain sink white porcelain
sink right and you keep cleaning it you
keep trying to clean it because there's
a hair I don't know man will understand
better than women
there's always hairs on the sink because
they're falling out right mr. funny so
you know and you keep rubbing and he
says no it's a scratch and your eyes
stop rubbing this thing stop trying to
fix your husband
stop trying to negotiate with your
husband stop trying to tell your husband
what
you need or why he's wrong or how he
should greet you at the door okay why
he's the hair on the seam what is a
scratch on your own eye okay it's a
scratch on it's a defect in you don't
talk to don't try to talk to him it's
hopeless
you already knew that in this system you
can fix she got the husband to cook and
wash the dishes without talking to him
there was no negotiation
she wasn't reasonable and she didn't
blackmail okay
she just fixed him at the source we're
here it was so cool there was no
discussion that he should wash the
dishes ever and there was no hint that
he should cook but she forced him to him
she forced him to cook and wash the
dishes now I have a deeper question you
want to go deeper if you if you answer
right you can HELOCs neck now what
happens if the man and the wife had come
to my talk together and the man is
sitting there thinking I'm going to use
the four steps to never ever ever wash
the dishes and the wife is thinking I'm
gonna use the four steps to make it make
and wash the dishes okay it's like the
Titanic meets the iceberg
which one will win how can both win I
mean he can't wash the dishes and not
wash the dishes a single object cannot
be two things at once
wait you didn't catch it a single thing
cannot be two things at once
right right Francesc this country two
things it can't be a better to throw the
same time here again and there could be
a dog's reality in this room and there
could be a human to be audience in this
room and they fit together quite nicely
okay got it physicists are just figured
out they say sixteen levels or some I
almost said a bad word the Buddha said
it a long time ago you know yeah of
course
in the man's world she'll be washing the
dishes in the woman's world he'll be
washing the dishes duh no problem don't
don't give me this thing that one thing
can't be both don't give me this thing
that two realities can't be going on in
the same room at the same time okay
that's easy that's a no-brainer
okay got it that's the Titanic question
okay one more and then I promise in
Mexico they call me Senor Ultima Ultima
Costa
mr. last thing okay hmm oh yeah number
four on page three is very interesting
it's called that confirmation it's
called duck confirmation okay so you and
your friend both went to the pan talk
okay you have a you're a woman you have
a lady friend and you both went to the
pen talk okay but your friend was
listening and you weren't okay then you
yell at your kids your friend is there
you know I don't know she heard through
the window while you're yelling at your
kids okay and then and then she happens
to be in the kitchen when you came in
okay got it
we got an independent witness educated
educated educated and Buddhism means
knows karma okay
she knows karma she went to the pen
talked she knows emptiness she saw you
misbehaving your kids sorry kids and
then she was there when you walked in
and the husband said you're stupid now
question for you how many husbands does
she see
yeah only one got it got it
she's your reality check she's are your
reality check she doesn't even see
husband number one why she wasn't
listening
during the pen garden she doesn't see
husband number one okay that's called
the confirmation of emptiness okay an
independent witness who understands
seeds walks into the room they don't see
a first husband they never saw a first
husband cuz there was no first husband
there if you don't have cataracts got it
cool all right if you agree it's cool
you can have a refreshment I'm gonna be
up here okay we're trying to keep the
three jewels healthy we were trying to
think of ways to keep them healthy we
raised the construction money it was a
lot it was like two three hundred
thousand dollars we did it and they have
a beautiful place and God bless now they
need rent money which is more perfidious
than construction money because it's
every month so we're we made this book
it was delivered by the printer an hour
ago this is a translation of the Diamond
Sutra and three other traditional
languages there's Chinese the
traditional Chinese edition there's the
traditional sounds good edition and
there's the traditional Tibetan Edition
all in one book for you to not read so
anyway I would really appreciate it we'd
really appreciate it if you buy one a
hundred percent of the money is going to
pay the rent add three jewels so we can
continue to have free free classes in
this kind of stuff and yoga paid yoga
classes and things like that okay so
where do they buy it table outside I
will sign them I did the translation I
finished it in travesty so I'll sign
books or if you just want to come up and
say hi I have a lot of old friends here
and please respect that other people
also want to say hi and I'm only here
once a year I think
okay let's see in about 15 minutes oh
say again okay I'll be down the stairs
near the book table okay thank you okay
[Applause]
[Music]
all right I forgot to tell you the
sounds good for the so it's--it article
is the star right and then Timmy Tom say
Timmy ROM and team Tim came into a lot
less timid to Mary to fear to be in the
dark and to be separated from happiness
okay and if you know Russian chimney
chimney comes from that it all means
darkness okay so that's a that's what
Tamina means okay so we have tariqa
Tamara and then we have Depot okay ste
ste Depot Depot means a butter lamp okay
by the way I'm gonna test you there's a
big debate in Buddhism is this verse
about impermanent or is this verse about
emptiness okay there's a big controversy
for two thousand years is this verse in
this verse is the Buddha teaching
impermanence which is how we use it in
the monks and the nuns so John we use it
as impermanence we snap our fingers
meaning I'm gonna be gone like that or
or does it relate to emptiness so so far
how's the vote going first one was what
star impermanence or illusion yeah you
can say both good I mean if you didn't
have an explanation of it you would say
impermanence because they they fade
every morning okay but now that you had
an explanation of the dark being the
misunderstanding in your mind and the
star being husband number one
now you understand it relates to
illusion also okay so it's kind of 50/50
on the first one how about the timid or
the really called cataract mostly
illusion are mostly impermanent
kind of illusion yeah that's the
impermanence yeah
it's also improvement that's right so so
far I think we got about a fifty-fifty
vote okay third one deep deeper comes
from a Sanskrit root deep which came
into English
do in the European due which came into
daiva or divine meaning God in in in
Latin is Jew
it's pronounced Jew and then the Father
in the sky is the Jupiter which is
Jupiter ok so that also comes from do so
Zeus comes from do you Tuesday comes
from - ok meaning a light a lamp ok and
we have a butter lamp there are six
meanings to the butter lamp okay number
one the scene in the kitchen requires
requires trigger and a fuel trigger and
a fuel ok the trigger is compared to the
wick of the butter lamp so I don't know
in in Tibet every December something we
have to celebrate some couples birthday
the young monks don't look forward to it
because they have to make by hand the
wicks for the thousand butter lamp
offerings which happen in every house it
takes about 3 months to make the wigs
you got to sit there all day and make
cotton into wicks you see so that's
their called linear linkage you
it means the material cause of the fire
the thing that flops into the fire and
then there's called authentic chicken
which is a contributing cost which is
the butter ok so you need a to have this
ignorance go on you have to have a main
seed and you have to have fuel fuel for
it to continue so we say when I yelled
at the kids
ok that's called karma freshly planted
in in in Sanskrit it's sanskara ok
freshly planted karma like when you
first plant a watermelon seed in the
spring you know you put it in the ground
and you cover it you know and then then
we call it son's color at that point
it's called fresh karma and the seed is
freshly planted in your mind then a week
goes by and I don't know what's
happening in the karmic seed but it
it I like to think it's like a little
factory and people are running around
and yelling and you know we got to get
this spout out and you know like it's a
miracle if you're a gardener like I'm a
gardener when you plan a scene and and
then what's happening between April and
June something's going on inside the
seed like a like Santa Clauses help us
are down there doing something and then
suddenly it breaks open okay just before
it breaks open we call it vasana okay so
a seed a fresh karmic seed is called
sanskara which means I just yelled at my
kids okay or I just gave dad the hundred
dollars which is Francis's when he goes
to college okay so that's called son's
car the first moment is called son's car
and then just before it opens we call it
vaasana' okay that's nut means something
has caused a seed to mature inside okay
something has caused the seed to mature
inside and we have separate explanations
for good seeds and bad seeds okay and
what's very interesting I mean very very
interesting what makes a seed go from
Sun scholar to vasana what makes a seed
go from fresh to pregnant and ready to
crack open okay
it's misunderstanding the scene okay
it's very weird okay because you don't
understand how you plant a seed with the
kids that misunderstanding also scaried
with prana and that prana causes
negative seeds to get fat and pregnant
and to open okay if you didn't
misunderstand the first husband your
Karma's couldn't open okay so we say you
cannot destroy a karma
because there's a justice to the
universe if you do if you hurt someone
you must get something bad if you help
someone you must get something good not
no power in the universe can destroy a
karma we say that okay but if they don't
get water yeah really and and a million
Karma's can sit on the tip of a needle a
billion comets can sit on the tip of a
needle karmic seeds in your mind inside
your brain they can live indefinitely so
you can kind of arrange for all your bad
Karma's to be put into suspended
animation or something and it doesn't
break the rules of Justice you see
they're still there they're still bad
they can still open but as long as you
don't misunderstand them they are
damaged okay there and they cannot open
properly okay
what's the opposite if you make a good
karma yeah you rejoice okay prana flows
with the thought long-stem chupa-chupa
prana flows with thoughts so if you
think about a kindness that you've done
for another person or you think about a
kindness you've seen someone else do for
another person then we say your Karma's
will open faster okay they will also go
from Sun scar to bust no faster good
Karma's okay that's why we say step
number four in planning a karma is every
night before you go to bed you just
think of all the sweet things you saw
today whether it was you or somebody
else so instead of thinking about Trump
just before you go to bed just think
about people you saw who had integrity
honesty good good people who are good
leading a good life and then all those
seeds will open okay that's very
important okay so you're the first image
of the lamp is that it needs fuel and it
needs a wig right the wick is your karma
the fuel is how you think about the
Karma
got in and and if you think about it
right
then bad karmas can't burn okay it's a
very interesting got it that's the first
image of the lamp okay second one if you
don't try to understand where the first
husband came from or the second now we
got a existential discussion did the
first husband come from any place
wait the first husband does not exist I
said never existed cannot exist now will
never exist in the future where do they
come from they don't exist
they don't exist okay we call rabbits
antlers okay now
no but it's a trick question because
obviously you can get angry at the first
husband right so there must be some
existence there okay and that's in your
mind as an imagination does a elephant
with two heads purple color exists no
but can you imagine it well yeah can you
get upset about it yeah okay all right
second one here if you don't understand
why the first husband was never there
the fire will spread to your kids next
week the fire will spread to your kids
next week and you will say something
again to your kids you see it's a cycle
it's a cycle and if you get if you get
in the habit of not understanding where
the husband really came from then it's
gonna burn it's gonna spread okay we
call aya Tana in Sanskrit Chiba in
Tibetan it means to a conflagration of
exponential fire it will spread like
crazy okay
all your relationships will be poisoned
if you can't learn that the first
husband was never there if you keep
accusing the husband of hurting you then
it will hurt your relationship with your
children it'll hurt relationships at
work okay
it's spreads this fire spreads the fire
of misunderstanding tends to spread
that's its nature it's like a fire okay
all right third one that's too complex
[Music]
none Tom say none thumb none means how
things appear in your life and thumb
means how things were never there which
is which in the husband which is the
appearance in which is the emptiness
which husband is emptiness yeah number
one he was never there
it wasn't ready do anything about that
one was never there that husband is
emptiness okay
the second husband is appearance why
it's flowing out of your mind
he's flowing out of your karma by the
way in case we don't get to it tonight
I'm gonna skip there in fact there's a
debate in the in a Buddhist monastery
okay they'll say you know is the first
husband real and you say no the first
husband never existed the one who I felt
that one never existed it's the second
husband real yeah does the second
husband have emptiness yeah he because
he can't be there if there's not the
space left by kicking out the first
husband okay
the first husband is impossible we
kicked him out of the kitchen
he was impossible then he left a space
that's where the second husband can be
he's the white screen that's the white
screen where the second husband can be
where's the second husband coming from
your mind your seat okay creating your
husband okay now there's a joke in the
monastery so a student will say yeah
even though he's coming from me he's
still real okay even though the second
husband is coming you can still get a
kiss from a husband who's flowing from
your mind okay
it's that good your mind is that good
okay I'm not kidding I said it's the pen
reel
yeah it's real is it coming from you
yeah even though it's coming from you
it's still real okay and some guy said
no it's not I said come here and get a
monster you know he's like no no that's
okay
I said then you think it's real right
well okay I think it's real yeah it's so
an immature debater in a Tibetan
monastery will say even though it's
coming from me it's real what will I'm
more mature debater say who said that
you're cheating you already know this
stuff yeah a more mature debater will
say it's real because it's coming from
me which means anything that's not
coming from you is not real got it
so don't go apologizing for your karmic
seeds oh you know everything's coming
from my mind but it still works The
Guardian says ah that sucks don't talk
like that okay everything's coming from
my mind it that makes it real got it
don't still apologize for your karma
it's coming from me but it's still real
I shut up oh it's coming from Mill and
then it and that makes it real that's
better okay got it
just nod okay anyway so in in in in
Buddhism we talked about we always talk
about the projector and the empty screen
okay the projector and the empty screen
the projector is your own mind the movie
that's loaded into it happened with the
kids
okay the movie was loaded and then I
walked into the kitchen and the movie
plane okay got it
and the movie needs an empty screen tell
me what's the empty screen huh the
absence of no more yeah and that allows
number two to have a place okay for
projection so anyway this Lama wants to
say lamps stand for the projection
cataracts stand for the emptiness and
stars stand for the marriage of
emptiness and projection that's just one
guy's opinion alright next guy yeah
number four is the well I just talked
about the gardener says refusal he says
don't say
things are coming from me but still
they're real I hate that who said that
the gardener okay he said don't say that
say they're they're coming from there
real because they're coming yeah he says
don't use but still I want to hear
because from you okay got it
all right next one page five tomorrow's
gonna be a wild day all right
[Music]
one llama objects to the lamp always
being used to demonstrate pain he says
don't call the wick a bad seed and don't
call the fuel misunderstanding the seeds
and the misunderstanding makes the bad
seed open harder don't keep talking like
that cuz good things also come that way
you know good things also come from
seeds and there's fuel for good things
also what's the fuel for a good seed
your rejoicing just before you go to bed
okay and it's so cheap
and it's so powerful you know they say
you can get 10% of another person's
karma if you're just happy about what
they're doing before you fall asleep
because the state of sleep is so
powerful and it goes on for so many
hours
just slightly enjoying someone else's
goodness before you sleep you get 10%
for free you don't have to do anything
okay it's very famous it's it's repeated
in many scriptures you know you want to
have it easy I mean if you understand
this stuff you can have a life which is
extremely financially successful you can
be very healthy you can have beautiful
beautiful relationships you can have
beautiful meditation and your life is
just like magical and we do it we have
that kind of life we just want you to
try we we haven't it's weird it's like
supernatural you know and money just go
you know and and people are just all
over the world we have 20,000 people
studying
weird stuff you know 800 Muslims in
Almaty I can't even say the name when we
were going what's the other place north
of there the capital the new capital
asana yeah Astana anyway I can't
pronounce the name of the cities and
they're wild about this stuff okay
and then in in my own country people are
anyway okay
all right number six life is a candle
okay that's uh that's easy I put that
one there because it's an American
expression right
life is a candle it will burn down when
you're born they light the candle okay
and it starts to burn and no one can
slow it down and no one can stop it okay
it's just burning everyday you're
burning I went to in in the monastery
Yoga is secret physical Yoga is secret
and you only learn it when you learn
Tantra so and you have to be a guess
eight to qualify for that so then you
know when you become a gesh a suddenly
you find out this nerd in the monastery
is a yoga teacher you know and you're
like wow I never thought it was you you
know he's a yeah it's me and and then
one day I remember I was walking home
and I and I met the the nerd and his
friend you know I said where have you
been I said why I just did a yoga class
and and they they said well how long was
it night and I was very proud I said it
was two hours
and they said why are you doing your guy
said I want to be healthy they said you
you two hours closer to dying man
that yoga class discussion two hours of
your life what are you talking live
longer you get it that's life as a
candle that's the sixth interpretation
of the candle okay life goes very fast
and it starts burning I say it a lesser
emptiness and a lesser comfort a lesser
emptiness and a lesser comfort there's a
form of emptiness there's another kind
of emptiness which is not as powerful it
like what are you calling great B
emptiness okay and it's where you also
have a feeling that your relationship
will last you see you you also have a
instinctual feeling that your
relationship will last and that's a
mistake okay
it's a misperception all relationships
pass and the people in relationships die
it's a question who dies first it's not
a question of whether right so and all
uncomfortable situations in the kitchen
also die you know sooner or later you
get along for a day okay so they say
even pain is impermanent you see so
that's supposed to be a comfort okay you
know the troubles you're having will
sooner or later go away either you'll
die they'll die or you'll make up okay
and that's a lesser emptiness that's a
lower school's emptiness it's a
consolidometer Akbar it's the rough form
of the lack of self to a person in the
I'll be done with school okay
things will change things will change
it's a comfort but not much right I
would rather live forever and I'd rather
my husband or my wife live forever okay
all right and you can if if things are
coming from you you can okay that's why
we're here all right
ten more minutes I'm going to start the
rabbit coming out of the Hat
which is called we say thorocotomy ROM
Depot Maya say Maya Maya as you know
means illusion okay and they're gonna go
into some of the meanings of illusion
okay and that's the continuum people
fourth of the nine messages from the
final verse of the diamond color is Maya
things are Maya
okay then different llamas say different
things there are nine different
interpretations here okay first one
your job your family and yourself
we are always deluded we're always
tricked into believing they are coming
from someplace other than where they are
really coming from and you know now
they're coming from how you treated the
kids last week okay that's all
so the first meaning of illusion in
Buddhism is that you didn't figure out
where your husband's coming from where
his behaviors coming from where
everything is coming from it's an
illusion you think it's coming this way
and in fact the word in Tibetan for a
person who doesn't understand things
it's sort of do you know it's or tone
sore tongue means people who think
things are incoming people who think
things are coming this way it's the
opposite of ayah okay so Tom means
incoming fear they see things coming
this way
okay so that's an illusion okay we
believe the world is coming at us when
actually the world is coming from us
okay so that's the first meaning of
illusion in the diamond cutter okay
second one even that tongue is a broken
instrument of perception okay even the
tongue tastes wrong yawa right even the
tongue is mistaken even even your senses
are defective okay your senses make
decisions about where stuff is coming
from I like this I like honey it's a
sweet I don't like eggplant it shouldn't
be a food okay no it's true but it's
coming from this way eggplants are
coming this way okay it's the only thing
okay
and but even your tongue is fooled in
your tongue believes that sweetness is
coming from the honey when actually it's
coming from you okay
it's very interesting and and things
that taste bad are also coming from
there's nothing in anything there's
nothing in anything
there's no sweetness in any food there's
no bad taste in any food okay it's all
coming from you when your tongue hits
the honey the the taste is flowing this
way okay it's coming from you okay it's
very interesting okay when your husband
yells at you and you feel hurt the
emotion the pain is coming from you you
see it's very interesting so I'm guess
there's wives who love to have husbands
yell at them or something it's like the
pen okay okay I didn't meet them but
okay number three then they start to
talk about there's a very famous famous
story in in Buddhism about magician the
village magician and if you've ever
lived in India village magicians are
cool before the internet there were the
coolest thing in India and they're very
very amazing and they have incredible
skills and they they're Rascals and they
can make they will take a piece of wood
it's called do you in Tibetan and
they're thrown on the ground and then
they do a mantra
they have special mantras and they have
a special powder
they throw them piece of wood on the
ground and they go for and they say the
original meaning of mantra was magic
spell so they'll do mantra and they'll
throw powder and suddenly everybody sees
a horse okay suddenly although everybody
and I've been there and it's weird and
you really see a horse and you're like
whoa and you have this you get everybody
backs up it's really just a piece of
wood on the ground like this big but
because of the mom turn because of this
powder everybody in the audience sees a
horse you know
and then somebody who comes up later
will say well why is everybody so
excited there's just a piece of wood on
the ground you know because they didn't
get the mantra and they didn't get that
then they say that's an example for
understanding emptiness
so the lady who came into the kitchen
without hearing about the pen first
she's like the the people got fooled by
the mantra okay got it
she's like the person who's under the
magic spell okay she thinks her husband
is coming from him she sees a mean
husband who I didn't do anything she
says I didn't do anything husband okay
she's like the person who got that
mantra on them okay who's the now that
does the magician see the horse yeah he
sees it cuz he got the month or and he
got the powder but does he believe it no
he knows he's seen something false okay
that's a person who went to Lincoln
Center and got the pen talk okay then
they're gonna go home tonight their
husband's gonna yell at them well where
are you and you know and they're gonna
say you didn't fool me then he'll get
more angry so we say that that person is
like the magician okay the one who went
to the talk at Lincoln Center and heard
about the husband and comes home and the
husband's angry she will be calm you
know for at least a few minutes by the
way in the beginning it lasts about that
long okay your memory of this talk will
fade within 24 hours and then the next
day you'll be upset okay but if you go
home right now quick don't go anywhere
else and just pray that your partner's
angry when you get there you can
practice okay now what about the we call
by the way that's J talk
gentle yes that's an aria after they saw
emptiness directly but now they still
see the thing coming this way okay so
there's possibilities like that is there
anybody who just doesn't see their
husband number one
yeah I mean like a very highly trained
person okay a very very highly trained
person they just over it you know
they're they understand they don't even
see the first husband okay
all right now illusion the meaning of
illusion in in the ancient times is
called the discrepancy okay and then
we'll stop okay
it's called the discrepancy between what
and one that's the meaning of Maya if
anyone ever asks you you know what is
this sounds good were in my I mean
illusion what does it mean you can say
it's a discrepancy
it looks like it's I didn't do anything
okay but it's really I did do something
okay got it
that's the meaning evolution okay I'll
say it again a discrepancy between the
way a thing appears in the way it really
is is the definition of Maya in in
Buddhism there's a discrepancy between
where he really came from and where it
looks like he came from it looks like he
had a bad day at work okay what's real
is that you yelled at the kids last week
okay so they're they don't match okay
those two understandings don't match
that's called minor then that's all that
illusion means in in in India it means
that the way it seems to be he seems to
be coming this way and the way he really
is don't match that discrepancy is
called illusion okay Maya got it
so how do you how do you get caught in
mire
yeah or yell back at the husband right
yell back at which one which the husband
number one you're yelling at not nobody
you're yelling at no one when I was in
Ukraine and we taught the husband the
two husbands you know we were talking
about it afterwards with some Ukrainians
they 100 million people died in World
War two and a lot in Ukraine and and
they were looking at me and they said
let me get this straight if what you say
is true then the husband you yell at is
the one who's not there am i right
yeah that means every enemy you ever had
in your life wasn't there it's not a
question of how you feel about them or
you should be compassionate or it's not
about that
they literally weren't there okay the
one you hated
whereas I need to intervene the country
who's fought your country I didn't do it
we didn't do anything you know the
country you're angry on doesn't exist
the people be them Arabs Russians just
whatever you choose somebody the ones
you hate they don't exist they never
existed every war fought on this planet
every casualty every death 100 million
in World War two was the result of
nobody there is no enemy it's coming is
there an enemy in the kitchen now
there's a guy flowing out of how you
treated your kids how can you get angry
the enemy is not there yeah get it
couldn't be there wasn't there never
will be there got it okay so as a result
of this compassion should be easier it's
not and you have to practice practice
practice okay basically you have to wash
your brain you see I mean you have to
stop your old way of thinking okay
anytime someone hurts you the instant
reaction should be what did I do
who did I yell at you know then then
you're not fighting back then you're not
you cannot fight back okay you you don't
have time you're trying to figure out
that's like the ultimate Buddhist in
song someone says and you're like you go
like that it means wait where the hell
did I plant you if you really want to
insult a Buddhist when they talk just
going okay well try to use it at home
tonight and tomorrow and I'll see you
tomorrow
and we'll go on thank you
[Applause]